A Guide to the Thomas W. Colley Collection, 1845-1947, 1986
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Thomas W. Colley Collection, 1845-1947, 1986
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2003-017
1.3 cu. ft. 3 boxes
The Thomas W. Colley Collection contains correspondence, financial documents, such as ledgers, receipts, and deeds, temperance society sermons, electoral cards, a Veteran's Meeting minute book, Civil War reminiscences, and a roll for the First Virginia Company D Volunteer Cavalry's wounded and dead for 1861. The majority of the collection dates from 1860 to 1920.
Colley, Thomas W., 1837-1919
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Special Collections before 2003.
Biographical Note
Thomas W. Colley (1837-1919) served in the Confederate army during the American Civil War. He enlisted in May 1861 as a private in the 1st Virginia Cavalry, Company D (2nd), referred to also as the Washington Mounted Rifles, as this company hailed from Washington County, VA. Colley was wounded multiple times during the course of the war. Most seriously, at Kelly's Ford in 1863, he was shot near the stomach on the left side; the ball passed clean through his body and emerged near his spine. He recovered and returned to his division. He finished the war with the rank of 2nd Corporal. Thomas Colley's brother, William Lewis Colley, who appears in correspondence within the collection, also served in the same cavalry division. Following the war, Colley returned to Abingdon, VA and held the following positions for Washington County, VA: Deputy Sheriff, Commissioner of Revenue, and Overseer for the Poor. He died in 1919.
Sources Consulted:
Driver, Robert J., Jr. 1st Virginia Cavalry. Lynchburg, VA: H. E. Howard, Inc., 1991.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains both material related to Thomas W. Colley's daily life in Abingdon, VA, and to Colley's service as a Confederate soldier in the Civil War. Materials include correspondence, financial documents, such as ledgers, receipts, and deeds, temperance society sermons, electoral cards, a Veteran's Meeting minute book, Civil War reminiscences, and a roll for the First Virginia Company D Volunteer Cavalry's wounded and dead for 1861. The majority of the collection dates from 1860 to 1920.
Much of the correspondence occurs between Thomas Colley and his extended family, except for Colley's business correspondence. The letters dating to the Civil War are typed transcriptions rather than the original. Later letters, however, that make reference to and reminisce about the Civil War are original.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: Series 1: Correspondence; Series 2: Financial Documents; and Series 3: Subject Files. The folders within each series are organized in chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Other materials relating to Thomas W. Colley can be found within the L. C. Angle, Jr. Collection, Ms 2001-043. available online.
Index Terms
Persons:
Colley, Thomas W., 1837-1919
Subjects:
Abingdon (Va.); Civil War; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Geographical Names:
Washington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Correspondence,1855-1986
  - Lewis Ballard Letter, 1855 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Family Correspondence, 1856-1934 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1860-1919 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Transcriptions of Civil War Letters & Associated Research Notes, 1861-1864, 1986 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence Related to the Civil War, 1863-1918 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Business Correspondence, 1866-1934 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Lamar Fontaine Letters, 1912-1914, 1946 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Financial Documents, 1845-1930
  - Bills, Statements, Receipts, 1845-1930 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Ledgers, 1856-1887 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Taxes, Washington Co., 1861-1862 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Deeds, 1873-1917 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Deed Transfers, 1905 (Box-folder 2-3)
- Subject Files,1848-1947, n.d.
  - Christopher Colly, 1848-1874 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - James Ryan, 1856-1928 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - 1st VA Co. D Vol. Cavalry Roll, 1861 - Civil War Wounded/Dead, 1861-1886 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Journal Subscriptions, 1873-1896 (Box-folder 2-7)
    Bibliography
    The Companion: A Monthly Magazine for Odd Fellows and Their Families. Vol. 13, No. 1 (August 1873).
    The Companion: A Monthly Magazine for Odd Fellows and Their Families. Vol. 14, No. 2 (March 1874).
    Self Culture: A Magazine of Knowledge. Vol II., No. 5 (February 1896).
  - Postcards, 1884-1947 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Alms House, "Poor" House, 1885-1887 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Advertisements, 1886-1923 (Box-folder 2-10)
  - "An Event in the Life of a Confederate Soldier", 1887 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - William E. Jones Camp Veterans Meeting Minutes and Related Correspondence, 1887-1905 (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Temperance Sermons and Materials, 1891-1903 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Election Tickets, 1893 (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Candidacy & Business Cards, 1895-1907 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Gen. Joseph Wheeler, Newspaper Article/Memorial Service, 1906 (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Publications and Printed Materials, 1911-1918 (Box-folder 3-5)
    Virginia Railway and Power Company, Rules and Regulations for the Government Employes of the Virginia Railway and Power Company. New York, 1912.
    Machen, Lewis H. Legal Handbook for Guidance of Soldiers and Sailors. Richmond, VA: Appeals Press, 1918.
    Practical Instruction Manual for Learners of Telegraphy. Philadelphia: A. F. Fleischmann's Electric Works.
  - John M. Colley, Pvt. Battery E, 35th Coast Artillery, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Obituary of S. C. Collop, n.d. (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Statement Against W. J. Porter, n.d. (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Etching, Thomas Wilkerson, n.d. (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Hand-drawn Map, Unidentified, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)